Guide to the Laura Aguilar Papers and Photographs, 1981-1995.
Department of Special Collections
Laura Aguilar Papers and Photographs,
1981-1995.
Special Collections M829
Aguilar, Laura
2.75 linear feet.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Provenance:
Acquired from Laura Aguilar, 1996.
Acquisition Information:
Purchased from Laura Aguilar, 1996.
Access Restrictions:
Consult Special Collections staff.
Biographical Note:
Laura Aguilar is a photographer whose works are mostly portraits. Professor Chon Noriega of UCLA's Department of Film and Television writes that Aguilar's work documents "social groups and identities that remain invisible in mainstream culture: Latina lesbians, black couples, obese people, et al." She cooperates with her subjects so that "her work is not about power differentials between photographer and subject as is often, if implicitly, the case with...the social documentary tradition." An autobiographical element is also apparent in Aguilar's work. Art critic Diana Emery Hulick noted that "the circumstances of [Aguilar's] life are reflected overtly in her art." Aguilar, Hulick wrote, "is large, lesbian, and Chicana, acutely aware of her separateness, yet comfortable enough with herself to present us with a personal vision that is both intimate and authoritative."
Laura Aguilar was born in west San Gabriel Valley, California in 1959. She has studied in the East Los Angeles Community College photography program and the Santa Fe Photographic Workshop, among other programs. In 1994/95 she was the recipient of a California Arts Council Fellowship and in 1991/92 of an Artist's Project Grant from Los Angeles Contemporary Exhibitions (LACE). Her work has appeared in exhibits in California, Texas, New York, and Mexico. Collections of her work can be found at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art and the Santa Monica Cultural Affairs Department in Santa Monica, California. Aguilar lives in Rosemead, California.
Diana Emery Hulick "Laura Aguilar," Latin American Art 5:3 (1993), 52-54.
Scope and Contents Note:
The Aguilar Papers and Photographs include the personal and professional materials of Laura Aguilar and occupy 2.75 linear feet. The collection traces through correspondence with mentors and friends both Aguilar's artistic development and her struggle with dyslexia. Her professional achievements are detailed in the series on exhibitions and published works. The print series includes original prints of three of Aguilar's photographic series: Latina Lesbians, Plush Pony, and Clothed/Unclothed.
The papers total 7 boxes and are arranged in the following series:
Correspondence
Exhibitions and Published Works
Prints
Cuadros, Gilbert.; House, Suda.; Martel, Pat.; Tenneson, Joyce.; Dyslexia.; Hispanic American lesbians.; Mexican American art.; Obesity.; Photography.; Photoprints.
Container Listing
- Series I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Deborah Bright, The Passionate Camera, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - CreArte, pART, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gilbert Cuadros, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters of recommendation for Aguilar, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Letters on photos," 1987-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pat Martel, 1990-92 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Siobhan Somerville, Purdue University, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Joyce Tenneson, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Joyce Tenneson, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Biennale di Venezia, 1993 (Box 2 (legal), Folder 1)
  - Suda House, 1980-90 (Box 2 (legal), Folder 2)
- SERIES II. EXHIBITIONS AND PUBLISHED WORKS
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1986 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 1)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1987 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 2)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1989 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 3)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1990 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 4)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1990 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 5)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1990 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 6)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1991 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 7)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1991 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 8)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1992 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 9)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1992 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 10)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1992 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 11)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1993 (Box 3 (legal), Folder 12)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1993 (Box 4 (legal), Folder 1)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1994 (Box 4 (legal), Folder 2)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1994 (Box 4 (legal), Folder 3)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1994 (Box 4 (legal), Folder 4)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1995 (Box 4 (legal), Folder 5)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1995 (Box 4 (legal), Folder 6)
  - Exhibitions and published works, 1995 (Box 4 (legal), Folder 7)
  - Exhibitions organized and curated by Aguilar, 1989-92 (Box 4 (legal), Folder 8)
  - Exhibitions, workshops, conferences, 1987-90, n.d. (Box 4 (legal), Folder 9)
  - Other Work (Box 5 (OS))
  - Luz Calvo, paper draft, 1995 (Box 5 (OS), Folder 1)
  - Certificate, honorable mention, for Mexican exhibit, 1988 (Box 5 (OS), Folder 2)
  - Elan (East Los Angeles College: Winter 1980) (Box 5 (OS), Folder 3)
  - Photo Nation, 1992and undated (workshop) (Box 5 (OS), Folder 4)
  - Square Peg (Dec./Jan. 1992/93) (Box 5 (OS), Folder 5)
  - "Writing about being dyslexia [sic] at Pasadena City College," 1983 (Box 5 (OS), Folder 6)
  - Nueva Luz, v. 4, no. 2 (1993) (Box 5 (OS), Folder 7)
- SERIES III. PRINT SERIES
  - Latina Lesbian series, 1986-1990 (Box 6 (OS), Folder 1)
  - Clothed/Unclothed series, list of photos (Box 7 (OS), Folder 1)
  - Clothed/Unclothed series, 1990-94,nos. 1-17 (Box 7 (OS), Folder 2)
  - Clothed/Unclothed series, 1990-94,nos. 18-34 (Box 7 (OS), Folder 3)
  - Plush Pony series, 1992 (Box 7 (OS), Folder 4)
FREQUENTLY-MENTIONED ORGANIZATIONS AND INDIVIDUALS
Prominent institutions in the collection include:
Biennale di Venezia
Los Angeles Contemporary Exhibitions (LACE)
Los Angeles County Museum of Art
Prominent or frequently-mentioned individuals include:
Gilbert Cuadros
Suda House
Pat Martel
Joyce Tenneson